<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-holmberg-mmusic-t140-usage-data-channel-latest" obsoletes="" updates="RFC8373" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="T.140 Data Channel">
       T.140 Real-time Text Conversation over WebRTC Data Channels
    </title>
    <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
  
    <date year="2019"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>MMUSIC Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SDP</keyword>
    <keyword>ITU-T</keyword>
    <keyword>T.140</keyword>
    <keyword>Data Channel</keyword>
    <keyword>WebRTC</keyword>
    <keyword>real-time text</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies how a WebRTC data channel can be used as a
        transport mechanism for Real-time text using the ITU-T Protocol for multimedia
        application text conversation (Recommendation ITU-T T.140), and
        how the SDP offer/answer mechanism can be used to negotiate
        such data channel, referred to as T.140 data channel.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
        The ITU-T Protocol for multimedia application text conversation (Recommendation ITU-T T.140)
        <xref target="T140"/> defines a protocol for text conversation, also known as
        real-time text. The native transport for IP networks is the "RTP Payload for Text Conversation"
        <xref target="RFC4103"/> mechanism, based on the Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP) <xref target="RFC4103"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document specifies how a WebRTC data channel <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>
        can be used as a transport mechanism for T.140, and how the SDP offer/answer mechanism
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/> can be used to negotiate such data channel.
      </t>
      <t>      
        In this document, a T.140 data channel refers to a WebRTC data channel for which
        the instantiated sub-protocol is "t140", and where the channel is negotiated
        using the SDP-based external negotiation method <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        NOTE 1: This WebRTC term of a "T.140 data channel" is actually
        synonym to the originally introduced concept of a "T.140 data
        channel" for the T.140 protocol, see Section 4.3
        of <xref target="T140"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        NOTE 2: The decision to transport realtime text over a data channel,
        instead of using RTP based transport <xref target="RFC4103"/>, in WebRTC
        is constituted by use-case "U-C 5: Realtime text chat during an audio
        and/or video call with an individual or with multiple people in a conference",
        see Section 3.2 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The brief notation "T.140" is used as a synonym for the text
        conversation protocol according to <xref target="T140"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document is based on an earlier Internet draft edited by Keith Drage,
        Juergen Stoetzer-Bradler and Albrecht Schwarz.
      </t>
    </section>
 
    <section title="Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
        "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.sdp" title="SDP Considerations">
      <t>
        The generic SDP considerations, including the SDP Offer/Answer proceudres, for
        negotiating a WebRTC data channel are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.
        This section defines the SDP considerations that are specific to a T.140 data channel.
      </t>
      <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcmap" title="Use of dcmap Attribute">
        <t>
           An offerer and answerer MUST, in each offer and answer, include an SDP 'dcmap' 
           attribute <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/> in the SDP media
           descripton (m= section) <xref target="RFC4566"/> describing the SCTP association
           <xref target="RFC4960"/> used to realize the T.140 data channel.
        </t>
        <t>
          The offerer and answerer MUST include the subprotocol attribute parameter,
          with a "t140" parameter value, in the 'dcmap' attribute value.
        </t>
        <t>
          The offerer and answerer MAY include the priority attribute parameter and
          the label attribute parameter in the 'dcmap' attribute value. If the offerer
          includes a label attribute parameter, the answerer MUST NOT change the value
          in the answer.
        </t>
        <t>
          NOTE: As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>,
          when a data channel is negotied using the mechanism defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol"/>,
          the label attribute parameter value has to be the same in both directions. That rule also
          applies also to data channels negotiated using the mechanism defined in this document.
        </t>
        <t>
          The offerer and answerer MUST NOT include the max-retr, max-time and ordered
          attribute parameters in the 'dcmap' attribute.
        </t>
        <t>
          Below is an example of the 'dcmap' attribute for an T.140
          data channel with stream=3 and without any label:
        </t>
        <t>
          a=dcmap:3 subprotocol="t140"
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa" title="Use of dcsa Attribute">
        <t>
           An offerer and answerer MAY, in each offer and answer, include an
           SDP 'dcsa' attribute <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>
           in the m= section describing the SCTP association used
           to realize the T.140 data channel.
        </t>
        <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.trans" title="Maximum Character Transmission">
          <t>
            A 'dcsa' attribute can contain the SDP 'fmtp' attribute used to indicate
            a maximum character transmission rate <xref target="RFC4103"/>. The 'cps'
            attribute parameter is used indicate the maximum character transmission rate
            that the endpoint that includes the attribute is able to receive. The 'format' attribute
            parameter is not used with T.140 data channels, and MUST be set to "-".
          </t>
          <t>
            If the 'fmtp' attribute is not included, it indicates that no maximum character transmission
            rate is indicated. It does not mean that the default value of 30 applies <xref target="RFC4103"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            The offerer and answerer MAY modify the 'cps' attribute parameter value in subsequent
            offers and answers.
          </t>
          <t>
            NOTE: The 'cps' attribute parameter is especially useful when a T.140 data channel
            endpoint is acting as a gateway [<xref target="sec.gw"/>] and is interworking with
            a T.140 transport mechanism that have restrictions on how many characters can be sent
            per second.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.lan" title="Real-time Text Conversation Languages">
         <t>
            'dcsa' attributes can contain the SDP 'hlang-send' and 'hlang-recv' attributes
            <xref target="RFC8373"/> to negotiate the language to be used for the real-time
            text conversation.
        </t>
        <t>
            For a T.140 data channel, the modality is "written" <xref target="RFC8373"/>.
        </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir" title="Real-time Text Direction">
          <t>
            'dcsa' attributes can contain the SDP 'sendonly', 'recvonly', 'sendrecv' and
            'inactive' attributes <xref target="RFC4566"/> to negotite the direction in 
            which text can be transmitted in a real-time text conversation, following
            the procedures in <xref target="RFC3264"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            NOTE: A WebRTC data channel is always bi-directional. The usage of the 'dcsa'
            attribute only affects the direction in which implementations are allowed to
            transmit text on a T.140 data channel.
          </t>
          <t>
            The offer/answer rules for the direction attributes are based on the rules 
            for unicast streams defined in <xref target="RFC3264"/>, as described below. 
            Note that the rules only apply to the direction attributes.
          </t>
          <t>
            NOTE: As for any other attribute included in a 'dcsa' attribute, the direction 
            attributes only apply to the T.140 data channel for which the 'dcsa' attribute
            is used. They have no impact on other data channels.
          </t>
          <t>
            Session level direction attributes <xref target="RFC4566"/> have no impact
            on a T.140 data channel. An offerer and answerer MUST mark the direction of
            the text by sending a direction attribute inside ‘dcsa- attribute.
          </t>
          <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.neg" title="Negotiate Text Direction">
            <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.neg.off" title="Generating an Offer">
              <t>
                If the offerer wishes to both send or receive text on a T.140 data channel, it
                SHOULD mark the data channel as sendrecv with a ‘sendrecv’ attribute inside a 
                ‘dcsa’ attribute. If the offerer does not explicitly mark the data channel, a
                ‘sendrecv’ attribute inside a ‘dcsa’ attribute is implicitly applied.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer wishes to only send text on a T.140 data channel, it
                MUST mark the data channel as sendonly with a ‘sendonly’ attribute inside a 
                ‘dcsa’ attribute. 
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer wishes to only receive text on a T.140 data channel, it
                MUST mark the data channel as recvonly with a ‘recvonly’ attribute inside a 
                ‘dcsa’ attribute. 
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer wishes to neither send or receive text on a T.140 data channel, it
                MUST mark the data channel as inactive with a ‘inactive’ attribute inside a 
                ‘dcsa’ attribute. 
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer has marked a data channel as sendrecv (implicit or explicit) or
                recvonly, it MUST be prepared to receive T.140 data as soon as the state of
                the T.140 data channel allows it. 
              </t>
              <t>
                When the offerer receives an answer to the offer, if the answerer has marked a 
                data channel as sendrecv (implicit or explicit) or recvonly in the answer, the offerer
                can start to send T.140 data as soon as the state of the T.140 data channel allows it.
                If the answerer has marked the data channel as inactive or sendonly, the offerer MUST NOT
                send any T.140 data.
              </t>
            </section> 
            <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.neg.ans" title="Generating an Answer">
              <t>
                When the answerer accepts an offer, and marks the direction of the text 
                in the corresponding answer, the marking is based on the marking (explicit or implicit) 
                in the offer.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer marked the data channel as sendrecv (implicitly or explicitly), 
                the answerer MUST mark the data channel as sendrecv, sendonly, recvonly or inactive
                with a ‘sendrecv’, ‘sendonly’, ‘recvonly’ respective ‘inactive’ attribute
                inside a ‘dcsa’ attribute. If the answerer does not explicitly mark the data channel, a
                ‘sendrecv’ attribute inside a ‘dcsa’ attribute is implicitly applied.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer marked the data channel as sendonly, the answerer MUST
                mark the data channel as recvonly or inactive with a ‘recvonly’ respective
                ‘inactive’ attribute inside a ‘dcsa’ attribute. 
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer marked the data channel as recvonly, the answerer MUST
                mark the data channel as sendonly or inactive with a ‘sendonly’ respective
                ‘inactive’ attribute inside a ‘dcsa’ attribute. 
              </t>
              <t>
                If the offerer marked the data channel as inactive, the answerer MUST
                mark the data channel as inactive with a ‘inactive’ attribute inside a 
                ‘dcsa’ attribute.
              </t>
              <t>
                If the answerer has marked a data channel as sendrecv or recvonly, it MUST be
                prepared to receive data as soon as the state of the T.140 data channel allows
                transmission of data. 
              </t>
            </section>
          </section> 
          <section anchor="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.mod" title="Modify Text Direction">
            <t>
              If an endpoint wishes to modify a previously negotiated text direction 
              in an ongoing session, it MUST initiate an offer that indicates the new 
              direction, following the rules in <xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.neg.off"/>. 
              If the answerer accepts the offer it follows the procedures in
              <xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir.neg.ans"/>.
            </t>
          </section> 
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec.sdp.ex" title="Examples">
          <t>
            Below is an example of an m= section describing a
            T.140 data channel, where the maximum character
            transmission rate is set to 20, and the text
            transmission direction is set to "sendrecv".
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[

    m=application 911 UDP/DTLS/SCTP webrtc-datachannel
    c=IN IP6 2001:db8::3
    a=max-message-size:1000
    a=sctp-port 5000
    a=dcmap:1 label="text conversation";subprotocol="t140"
    a=dcsa:1 fmtp:- cps=20
    a=dcsa:1 sendrecv

            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Below is an example of an m= section of an offer 
            for a T.140 data channel offering real-time text
            conversation in Spanish and Esperanto, and an m= section
            in the associated answer accepting Esperanto.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[

Offer:

    m=application 911 UDP/DTLS/SCTP webrtc-datachannel
    c=IN IP6 2001:db8::3
    a=max-message-size:1000
    a=sctp-port 5000
    a=dcmap:1 label="ACME customer service";subprotocol="t140"
    a=dcsa:1 fmtp:- cps=30
    a=dcsa:1 hlang-send:es eo
    a=dcsa:1 hlang-recv:es eo

Answer:

    m=application 911 UDP/DTLS/SCTP webrtc-datachannel
    c=IN IP6 2001:db8::1
    a=max-message-size:1000
    a=sctp-port 5000
    a=dcmap:1 label="ACME customer service";subprotocol="t140"
    a=dcsa:1 fmtp:- cps=30
    a=dcsa:1 hlang-send:eo
    a=dcsa:1 hlang-recv:eo

            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.t140" title="T.140 Considerations">
        <section anchor="sec.t140.slf" title="Session Layer Functions">
          <t>
            Section 6.1 of <xref target="T140"/> describes the generic T.140 session
            control functions at high-level and a signalling protocol
            independent manner. The list below describes how the functions
            are realized when using a T.140 data channel.
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Prepare session: An endpoint can indicate its support of T.140 data channels
                using signalling specific means (e.g., using SIP OPTIONS <xref target="RFC3261"/>), or by indicating the support in an
                offer or answer (<xref target="sec.sdp"/>)</t>
              <t>Initiate session: An offer used to request the establishment of a
                T.140 data channel (<xref target="sec.sdp"/>)</t>
              <t>Accept session: An answer used to accept a request to establish a
                T.140 data channel (<xref target="sec.sdp"/>)</t>
              <t>Deny session: An answer used to reject a request to establish
                a T.140 data channel, using the generic procedures for rejecting
                a data channel <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/></t>
              <t>Disconnect session: An offer or answer used to disable a previously
                established T.140 data channel, using the generic procedures for closing
                a data channel <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/></t>
              <t>Data: Data sent on an established T.140 data channel (<xref target="sec.t140.send"/>)</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.t140.send" title="Data Encoding and Sending">
          <t>
            T.140 text is encoded and framed as T140blocks <xref target="RFC4103"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Each T140block is sent on the SCTP stream <xref target="RFC4960"/> used to
            realize the T.140 data channel using standard T.140 transmission procedures
            <xref target="T140"/>. One or more T140blocks can be sent in a single
            SCTP user message <xref target="RFC4960"/>. Unlike RTP based transport for
            realtime text <xref target="RFC4103"/>, T.140 data channels do not use redundant
            transmission of text. The reason for this is that the T.140 data channel achieves
            robust transmission by using the "reliable" mode of the data channel.
          </t>
          <t>
            Data sending and reporting procedures conform to <xref target="T140"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            See Section 8 of <xref target="T140"/> for coding details.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.t140.buff" title="Data Buffering">
          <t>
            As described in <xref target="T140"/>, buffering can be used to reduce
            overhead, with the maximum buffering time being 500 ms. It can also be used for
            staying within the maximum character transmission rate (<xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa"/>),
            if such has been provided by the peer.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation needs to take the user requirements for smooth flow and low
            latency in real-time text conversation into consideration when assigning a buffer time.
            It is RECOMMENDED to use the default transmission interval of 300 milliseconds
            <xref target="RFC4103"/>, or lower, also for T.140 data channels.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.t140.loss" title="Loss of T140blocks">
          <t>
            In case of network failure or congestion, T.140 data channels might fail and get torn down.
            If this happens but the session sustains, it is RECOMMENDED that a low number of 
            retries are made to reestablish the T.140 data channels. If reestablishment of
            the T.140 data channel is successful, an implementation MUST evaluate if any 
            T140blocks were lost. Retransmission of already transmitted T140blocks MUST be
            avoided, and missing text markers <xref target="T140ad1"/> SHOULD be inserted in the received 
            data stream where loss is detected or suspected.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation needs to take the user requirements for smooth flow and low
            latency in real-time text conversation into consideration when assigning a buffer time.
            It is RECOMMENDED to use the default transmission interval of 300 milliseconds
            <xref target="RFC4103"/>, or lower, also for T.140 data channels.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec.t140.mul" title="Multi-party Considerations">
          <t>
            If an implementation needs to support multi-party scenarios, the implementation needs
            to support multiple simultaneous T.140 data channels, one for each remote party. At
            the time of writing this document, this is true even in scenarios where each participant
            communicate via a centralized conference server. The reason is that, unlike RTP media,
            WebRTC data channels and the T.140 protocol do not support the indication of the source
            of T.140 data. The SDP 'dcmap' attribute label attribute parameter (<xref target="sec.sdp.dcmap"/>)
            can be used by the offerer to provide additional information about each T.140 data channel, and help
            implementations to distinguish between them.
          </t>
          <t>
            NOTE: Future extensions to T.140, or to the T140block, might allow indicating the source
            of T.140 data, in which case it might be possible to use a single T.140 data channel to
            transport data from multiple remote sources.
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.gw" title="Gateway Considerations">
      <t>
        A number of real-time text transports and protocols have been defined for
        both packet switched and circuit switched networks. Many are based on the 
        ITU-T T.140 protocol on application and presentation level <xref target="T140"/>. 
        At the time of writing this document, some mechanisms are no longer used, as
        the technologies they use have been obsoleted etc, while others are still in use.
      </t>
      <t>
        When performing interworking between T.140 data channels and another real-time text
        transports and protocols with real-time text in another, a number of factors 
        need to be considered.
        At the time of writing this document, the most common IP-based real-time text transport
        is the RTP based mechanism defined in <xref target="RFC4103"/>. While this document
        does not define a complete interworking solution, this list below provides some guidance
        and considerations to take into account when designing an gateway for interworking
        between T.140 data channels and RTP-based T.140 transport:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            For each T.140 data channel there is an RTP stream for real-time text <xref target="RFC4103"/> . 
            Redundancy is by default declared and used on RTP stream. On the T.140 data channel
            there is no redundancy, but the reliable property <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>
            of T.140 the data channel is set.
          </t>
          <t>
            During a normal text flow, T140blocks received from one network are forwarded towards the other network.
            Keep-alive traffic is implicit on the T.140 data channel. A gateway might have to extract keep-alives from
            incoming RTP streams, and MAY generate keep-alives on outgoing RTP streams.
          </t>
          <t>
            It is RECOMMENDED that the gateway uses the same transmission interval on both the T.140 data channel and the RTP stream,
            if possible. That will reduce the delay caused by buffering.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the gateway detects or suspects loss of data on the RTP stream, the gateway gateway SHOULD insert the T.140 missing
            text marker <xref target="T140ad1"/> in the data sent on the outgoing T.140 data channel. 
          </t>
          <t>
            If the gateway detects or suspects loss of data on the T.140 data channel, the gateway gateway SHOULD insert the T.140 missing
            text marker <xref target="T140ad1"/> in the data sent on the outgoing RTP stream. 
          </t>
          <t>
            If the gateway detects that the T.140 data channel has failed and got torn down, once the data channel has been reestablished
            the gateway SHOULD insert the T.140 missing text marker <xref target="T140ad1"/> in the data sent on the outgoing RTP stream
            if it detects or suspects that data on the T.140 data channel was lost.
          </t>
          <t>
            The gateway MUST indicate the same text transmission direction (<xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir"/>) on the T.140 data channel
            and the RTP stream.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        NOTE: In order for the gateway to insert a missing text marker, or to perform other actions that require that the
        gateway has access to the T.140 data, the T.140 data cannot be encrypted end-to-end between the T.140 data channel endpoint
        and the RTP endpoint. At the time of writing this document, a mechanism to provide such end-to-end encryption has not been defined.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec.8373" title="Update to RFC 8373">
        <t>
          This document updates RFC 8373, by defining how the SDP hlang-send and hlang-recv attributes are used for
          the "application/webrtc-datachannel" media type.
        </t>
        <t>
          SDP offerers and answerers MUST NOT include the attributes directly in the m= section associated with the
          'application/webrtc-datachannel' media type. Instead, the attributes MUST be associated with
          individual data channels, using the SDP 'dcsa' attribute. A specification that defines a subprotocol
          that uses the attributes MUST specify the modality for that subprotocol, or how to retreive the 
          modality if the subprotocol supports multiple modalities.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec.sec" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
          The generic security considerations for WebRTC data channels
          are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>. As data channels
          are always encrypted by design, the T.140 data channels will
          also be encrypted.
        </t>
        <t>
          The generic security considerations for the SDP-based external 
          negotiation method are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec.iana" title="IANA considerations">
      <t>
        [RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please replace all instances of RFCXXXX with the RFC number of this document.]
      </t>
      <section anchor="sec.iana.sub" title="Subprotocol Identifier t140">
        <t>
          This document adds the subprotocol identifier "t140" to the "WebSocket Subprotocol Name Registry" as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='30%'/>
          <ttcol align='left'/>

          <c>Subprotocol Identifier:</c>
          <c>t140</c>

          <c>Subprotocol Common Name:</c>
          <c>ITU-T T.140</c>

          <c>Subprotocol Definition:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>

          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="SDP fmtp Attribute" anchor="sec.iana.dcsa.fmtp">
        <t>
          This document modifies the usage of the SDP 'fmtp' attribute, if this attribute is
          included in an SDP 'dcsa' attribute and associated with an T.140 real-time text session
          over a WebRTC data channel. The modified usage is described in <xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.trans"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'fmtp' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>fmtp</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Indicate the maximum transmission rate that an endpoint is willing to recive on a T.140 data channel. 
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="SDP Language Attributes" anchor="sec.iana.dcsa.hlang">
        <t>
          This document modifies the usage of the SDP 'hlang-send' and 'hlang-recv' attributes, if these attributes are
          included in SDP 'dcsa' attributes associated with an T.140 data channel. 
          The modified usage is described in <xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.lan"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'hlang-send' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>hlang-send</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the language to be used on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'hlang-recv' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>hlang-recv</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the language to be used on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="SDP Media Direction Attributes" anchor="sec.iana.dcsa.direction">
        <t>
          This document modifies the usage of the SDP 'sendonly', 'recvonly', 'sendrecv' and 'inactive' attributes,
          if these attributes are included in SDP 'dcsa' attributes associated T.140 data channel. The modified usage
          is described in <xref target="sec.sdp.dcsa.dir"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'sendonly' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>sendonly</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the direction in which real-time text can be sent on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'recvonly' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>recvonly</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the direction in which real-time text can be sent on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'sendrecv' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>sendrecv</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the direction in which real-time text can be sent on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>
        <t>
          The usage level "dcsa(t140)" is added to the IANA registration of the SDP 'inactive' attribute as follows:
        </t>
        <texttable title="">
          <ttcol align='left' width='35%'/>
          <ttcol align='left' width='65%'/>

          <c>Contact name:</c>
          <c>MMUSIC Chairs</c>

          <c>Contact email:</c>
          <c>mmusic-chairs@ietf.org</c>

          <c>Attribute name:</c>
          <c>inactive</c>

          <c>Usage level:</c>
          <c>dcsa(t140)</c>

          <c>Purpose:</c>
          <c>
            Negotiate the direction in which real-time text can be sent on a T.140 data channel.
          </c>
       
          <c>Reference:</c>
          <c>RFCXXXX</c>
        </texttable>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.acks" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
      <t>
        This document is based on an earlier Internet draft edited by Keith Drage,
        Juergen Stoetzer-Bradler and Albrecht Schwarz.
      </t>
      <t>
        Thomas Belling provided useful comments on the initial (pre-submission) version
        of the draft. Gunnar Hellstrom provided comments and text on the draft.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4103"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4960"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8373"?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg'?>
      <reference anchor="T140">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation ITU-T T.140 (02/1998), "Protocol for
             multimedia application text conversation"</title>
          <author><organization>ITU-T</organization></author>
          <date year="1998" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-T.140-199802-I/en"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="T140ad1">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation ITU-T.140 – Addendum 1  (02/2000), "Protocol for
             multimedia application text conversation"</title>
          <author><organization>ITU-T</organization></author>
          <date year="2000" month="February"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-T.140-200002-I!Add1/en"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <reference anchor="V151">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation ITU-T V.151 (05/2006), "Procedures for the end-to-end connection of 
            analogue PSTN text telephones over an IP network utilizing text relay"</title>
          <author><organization>ITU-T</organization></author>
          <date year="2006" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-V.151/en"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="V152">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation ITU-T V.152 (09/2010), "Procedures for supporting voice-band data over 
            IP networks"</title>
          <author><organization>ITU-T</organization></author>
          <date year="2010" month="September"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-V.152/en"/>
      </reference>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
